so put it here in my front. I'm going to put those
take a look, so I calculated those here separately actually.
So this is also an option I just wanted to show.
all, let's see. I was thinking.
we'll..., it's true what you guys say hey, the GROUP BY and the COUNT.
I expected the solution after that, I don't have my preview on.
okay
So if we just adjust this query
To finalize it because apparently that slide is missing.
Indeed, we're going to group those by customer number.
That name is functionally dependent so you can put that in your GROUP BY as well.
Indeed, you just get a COUNT that you can put in there.
So you can say GROUP BY customer number and first name.
and you should leave out the k2 name
or you're going to do count of k2 name by.
So you can do that perfectly then.
We don't need that L1 anymore to see what the common initial is.
um, the common letter.
So that's just here for your information.
And then the other little example I just said hey, so without a letter we can also possibly work if we calculate those things separately.
okay.
Then we have another little example.
Non-scalar subqueries
What do we mean by a scalar subquery?
Remember? We had 4 types of subqueries.
We had table subqueries,
we had...
Abstractly, it's always a table of course,
but for certain dimentions we give it a different name.
So what do we mean by a scalar subquery?
Multiple rows and columns? Then we talk about a table subquery Lucas.
NIet-scalar, then we mean by that it is more than 1 row and 1 column.
So that's not scalar there.
So scalar subquery is just 1 times 1.
yes.
but we're talking about
non scalar subqueries
Subqueries that we know of that are not scalar.
You guys also know that if we put a subquery in the SELECT...
In the Select, yes then there should only be 1 value there.
If it says "SELECT customer number comma" there and then a subquery, only 1 value should come out of that.
that should be there, that's the only way you can add that in the SELECT, but what if it's not...
That then more than 1 value, how do we solve that?
Okay
So
This Here.
Is not a problem.
This is a Scalar subquery.
Hey, I'm looking up stuff here from travel,...
And I write a subquery in my SELECT and da maximum is 1 value.
And it's a correlated subquery.
By itself, no problem.
is it correlated or not, the important thing is that there is only one value here, so it executes perfectly.
You always have to keep in mind, does that take the form of a table, does that make sense?
So this is not a problem, but....
What if I put this now?
Then you will indeed get that error message.
That length of stay, that could be multiple lengths of stay here.
For the same trip they are probably multiple visits so also multiple lengths of stay.
so
Here comes trip 1 with 7 different verbiage.
Now you can think of yes, to me that makes sense. I can go back and supplement that like that latteral. But that's not how that works.
The standard is not so defined.
So it always expects 1 value there.
So then you get that error.
So how can we solve that? also with that latteral again.
so euh...
Aja this little example I can also give.
It should really be 1 times 1 for subquery, because here only 1 comes out, they are also agregation functions, comes out 1 row
but with 2 columns
You could of course solve this by splitting that into 2 correlated subqueries. 1 for sum,
1note for variance.
but okay.
Just show it for the sake of completeness for the people who...
That's a question I get sometimes.
So the solution here is lateral eh.
Yes, we're going to have our...
The thing that was in our SELECT we're going to move to our FROM.
We say we want all those trips.
But in addition to those trips, we want to take a look at each trip, what about the length of stay here, both the sum and the variance.
For that trip, and I'll add that.
And I'm going to show that then.
The word lateral is needed here because length of stay comes from travel.
From the table travel at one level higher.
okay
So then we get this here for example.
We get here variance 0
Yes, that means there is only 1 visit for that trip. 31
okay
We could also write that query just now, the first one I gave there without those aggregation functions.
If we have more than one value, we can do that too.
yes
Now these are a little bit of artificial examples. because of course we can also start doing this by....
visits moving up a level.
And start calculating those things.
okay
We can make combinations of those things.
That is, you can both...
Work with either that latteral.
We can start working with even agregation functions combined with an ordinary value, so that GROUP BY.
So you can actually start doing a fair amount of those things.
okay
This might be another one.
That I can show then.
So, you guys have already seen different agregation functions,
let's go back, yeah.
moment
Now that example is no longer there, that's okay.
So the COUNT you all know.
but what we just did with that UN NEST
so from a row
flat hey, back to normalizing the original value.
Can you also reverse denormalize with an agregation cucntion like array agregate, so then we put those together
So das also a way that you can work.
So then you get something like that, the reverse effect actually.
Then the most common case I think, so all the previous cases we've seen so far
Unless you're really with such a normlization/denormalization problem.
So that it's denormalized data that you have to go and normalize.
Most of the queries that we've seen so far you can probably find another alternative.
That you don't need that lateral, yes.
This is one where that lateral usually, yeah,...you're not going to be able to get around it usually.
So, we just saw the presentation of fetch first.
So we want to start comparing that to a limited dependent result.
So what does that mean?
okay
So,this is such an example? we have travel....
And we're going to join that with this subquery but there's a dependency there with that leteral.
So try to see once, what does this query do?
Ah sorry, I had turned my sound off for a moment with the drinking.
Good that Sasha reports that.
So, the hint from Rik indeed,
or the thing that Arthuur says there or Rik, it's about the 2 smallest or the 2 largest indeed.
So if we go through it step by step, we have the table travel here in the FROM.
All the trips are shown anyway, here, LEFT.
Then that's combined with any visits.
I see that in visits B2
And the WHERE condition here, it goes for this trip.
So the visitor of that trip.
And for visiting I'm going to look up, what sky objects are actually visited here?
And then I'm going to sort them by diameter, just the first 2....
show and retrieve.
So that basically means, I'm going to per trip only the first 2 objects....
Which are visited according to the diameter.
Now the question is of course how is this sorted? ORDER BY diameter.
Is that from small to large or from large to small?
If you don't remember that, is not a problem, I don't always do that either but that is indeed the system that is applied here, we will have a look.
okay
So what you see here I think when you see those diameters going up.
You see here, after a 32 it does indeed go over.
So the 2 smallest celestial objects per trip that are shown here
okay
good
So by comparison, we'll look that one up.
This was line 32.
Did I have trip number 32, I had an object of diameter 7 and 14.
So if I look up everything for example from 32
I find there indeed so from 7, 14 and all those other are bigger.
So I effectively get the 2 smallest objects what are visited on that trip.
okay
So most of the time you can indeed work without that lateral, but some problems you can idly solve without that lateral.
So when you're sitting with an example like that....
Like this right here.
When that you actually have a... it stands here... moment...
When you have to compare to a limited dependent outcome.
So that you actually think for example, I need a subquery.
Where I need that fetch first while I'm in an edependency.
Then 9/10 you're going to need that lateral anyway.
Or you're stuck with that little example from earlier with that row that you want to start denormalizing.
The one you want to go normalize sorry.
Then 9/10 you're going to need a lateral like that as well although sometimes that does require alternatives.
Other than that, you can actually write alternative queries quite often.
Then the only question is, if you write those queries....
If you know how then you can do that.
I have that way with lateral, I have that way without lateral , we are going to compare those cost prices to see, which query do I choose here of course?
That's what we're trying to do to you guys...
so perfomance is something, once you master databases, then you really do get into that area of performance.
okay
Are there any questions about that lateral?
Lateral joins.
okay